in from the lobby. Um it will take just
a moment. Um and so as people are
joining in from the lobby, um as usual,
good afternoon everyone. Thank you all
for uh waiting. We are letting everybody
in from the lobby right now. So please
give us a moment or so for that to
occur. It usually does take a minute or
two. In the meanwhile, my name is
Dominic Erllo and I'm uh the center
director for medical cannabis and
psilocybin at the department of health
and uh the department is just here and
our program is just here to help and
assist with the committee and so we have
several folks here who will be doing
just that. Um this is the education and
training committee with Brenda Bergard
who is the chair and so with that Brenda
I will turn it on over to you. Oh, uh,
sorry, my apologies, Brenda. I have one
last item. Almost forgot. Just as a
reminder to everybody that because this
is a public meeting and because we do
post these up onto the website, please
keep language appropriate and for those
uh who had not been on some of the
earlier meetings. The reason we do not
have everybody on with face but just a
couple of people at any given time is
because uh when we have so many people
in meetings and if they are on both
visually as well as uh audible uh then
what ends up happening is it takes up so
much bandwidth some of our uh folks who
are in areas where there it's more rural
or frontier areas tend to drop off the
call due to the internet connection a
little more often. So, we keep the band
try to keep the bandwidth a little lower
and so that's the reason we just don't
have everybody all on camera. Um, but we
appreciate it. Thank you all very much.
And Brenda, back to you. Sorry about
that.
>> Oh, that's quite all right. All right.
Well, thank you everyone for coming. I
really appreciate you being here. Um, I
know there's a lot of people out there
that are very knowledgeable about
education and training and uh this is
what this is all about. And um and if
you've been to other meetings, you'll
notice there's a little bit of overlap
here and there. There is going to be
some of that. Um but for right now,
we're going to try to stick to the
education and train training part of uh
this second meeting. And um if you
wanted to um Jorge, if you could bring
up uh the agenda on the PowerPoint
>> um on your PowerPoint. Is that is that
what you're asking?
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Let's see.
>> And while we're doing this, if anybody
wants to introduce themselves, they can
do so right now to just please raise
your hand.
All right. And um just reminder to raise
your hand there on Teams. There's a
raise icon um with a little hand icon up
at the top um left or centerish part of
the screen. Um like to hit that. We just
posted instructions in the chat um for
that as well.
All right, I see we have Harvey King.
Your hand is up and I have enabled your
mic. You can unmute when ready.
Hi, I hope everybody's doing well. I was
in the um improvement research committee
meeting this morning. newly just joining
these meetings and as a hospice nurse
interested in end of life use of
psilocybin and so uh excited to start to
be a part of all this. Thanks.
>> Awesome. Thank you. And next we've got
James Brown. Um James, your mic is
enabled. You can unmute when ready.
>> Afternoon Brenda and thank you again for
chairing this awesome committee. I do
appreciate you and all your efforts. Um,
so amazing. Um, everybody, my name is
James Brown. Uh, earlier, uh, you know,
I'm a farm D from New Mexico. Um, I'm
psychedelic facilitator trained in
psilocybin. Very excited to be part of
this. Um, thank you again.
Right. Thank you, James. Um, again, for
anybody who'd like to introduce
themselves, um, the instructions are in
the chat. Um, and the raise icon is um,
uh, towards the center left kind of part
of the top pane there. I see Gregory
Evans has his hand up.
And Greg, your mic is enabled. You can
unmute when ready.
>> Thank you. I think everyone's just
getting settled. There's a lot of people
in here that should be introducing. Um,
my name is Gregory Evans. I am an
independent researcher and homecologist
with no affiliations. I'm a Santa Fe
resident and my intention here is to
support the program's development
through committee recommendations which
are aligned with emerging research and
best practices.
Awesome. Thank you, Gregory. Um, and
also if you'd like to um introduce
yourselves in the chat um instead of
raising your hand and doing so audibly,
um you can enter in any information
you'd like in the chat as
All
right. Not seeing any more hands raised
right now. Um Brenda, if you want to go
over the agenda. Um and if anyone wants
to introduce themselves later, if they
have comments, um if you could just do
so before, um contributing to
conversation. Thanks.
>> All right. Thank you. All righty. So,
um, this is our second meeting. Um, and
I just wanted to put up a short little
PowerPoint here about what we're what we
need to cover. And so uh today's agenda
will be um looking over reciprocity
education and in the curriculum what the
um curriculum is going to have in it
that uh is specific to New Mexico and
New Mexico history
um cost training and education which I
don't really have a costs of what this
is going to be or what will be
allocated. So um you know there's a lot
of questions that need to be answered or
will be coming along um as time goes on.
So let's see uh let's go to the next
slide.
Okay. So I want to open this up to
everybody and I'll go ahead and read
this and then um uh have some comments
about this. Um so I wanted to target uh
the reciprocity and recognition of the
prior training because those of us have
been in training it from other states
like Oregon and Colorado
um and other places uh we want to make
sure that we're having enough
education to bring here into New Mexico.
However, a lot of us have spent a lot of
time and money learning how to do this
very specific training. And so when
we're when when we've done all of that,
we want to see if we can get going with
what we know already. And so we want to
build a framework that supports um these
pathways for all of us clinicians and
medical providers and spiritual care u
professionals um prior to psychedelic
related education or training um
completed in other jurisdictions.
Um so what I think we really need to
look at here is documentation for this
because um all of us have a variety of
different types of documentation
um syllabus that's uh very very um
uh
heavy in information and practicum. And
so when before New Mexico started taking
on this wonderful
uh practice, we had to go elsewhere to
learn how to do this. So I'm just
wondering how we are going to do this
with the department of health. Um and so
some of us have certification or
transcripts or both. Um, some of us have
some documentation of some sort that
could qualify for proof of, uh,
reciprocity.
Um, and so, um, I would like to know,
um, how many of you out there are kind
of in between, haven't really finished
any certification yet, but are in the
process somewhere else learning how to
do um, uh, this type of training. Just
raise your hands.
So, so there's a few people out there.
Um, so what does that mean? Um, so we're
going to um start to
get this together basically. You know,
what does this mean? Cuz I know some
people um we can't leave some people
out. We can't have exceptions. But then
again, we have to understand and
um bring this all together so we're able
to have people come in and start doing
this work. So, um let's see. Uh so I was
talking to Dominic earlier about, you
know, what is licensing going to be? And
so that's going to be, I think, a
totally different department. Um, for
those of us that are practitioners, um,
therapists, doctors,
uh, nurse practitioners, we're already,
we already have licenses. So, what does
that look like for us? So, I want to
pose a question to everyone out there.
Um, what would you like to see as far
as, um, your training goes? What would
you like to have New Mexico have in
their training program for reciprocity?
All right, I see Ann Mets hand up. Ann,
I have just allowed your mic. You can
unmute when ready.
>> Hi, my name is Ann Mets. Um, I'm a
licensed professional counselor and
national um, natural medicine
facilitator. I'm trained in Colorado.
Uh, I live in Tal County and I'm also
the director of Fluence's
um, clinical natural medicine
facilitation training program in
Colorado. And so I think um you know
wearing the hat as a training director I
think that having New Mexico's program
is largely um reflect what the other
states have required in terms of
training I think is is practical and
also in the best interest of students to
give them more options for training
programs. Um, and in terms of like
licensed reciprocity, I think if you're
licensed in Oregon or Colorado to
provide these services, I think that
that would be a really nice um just to
be able to have licensed portability in
New Mexico.
Thank you, Ann. And I think that's a
really important topic here is um
people who who ha who have been licensed
in other states, you know, getting
licensed here in New Mexico, what is
that going to look like? And
unfortunately, I don't have that
information, but I I think that we'll be
able to um bring that into New Mexico uh
for for training. And um uh so that
brings me into the next slide. Um let's
see what the next slide is. Okay. Um you
know, should should people be
grandfathered in? Um in other words, um
if you've been working in other states,
um like Ann has um and lives in to uh
yeah, you're definitely wearing two hats
here. And so, um, I think that, uh,
bringing people in that are already
doing the training and the education,
um, should be able to, um, practice here
in New Mexico. Um the other thing I was
thinking of and this was what I was um
uh trying to propose here is that um
people who already have certification
and training and are not here well
trained here in New Mexico cuz we're
just starting why not have like a 6 to 8
hour uh review of additional training
here for New Mexico so to meet the
qualifications here so we're not getting
bogged down with hours of training um
trying to trying to do this. And also
too, right before I had this meeting,
I'm like going well maybe um also too
once we start getting very close to
training and
getting this rolling like weeks before.
if any of us who are certified uh need
extra practicum and that would just be
maybe another, you know, um 6-hour day
or something like that uh to get your
feet wet and that would be, you know, uh
just an extra added, you know, bonus for
your education here in New Mexico. But
however, if you're already here in New
Mexico, I wanted to kind of keep that as
a um an add-on uh just if you needed
refresher. For instance, if you you know
been certified like years ago but have
not been able to um practice or, you
know, for protection of your own license
um kind of shelf it for a while. Uh
yeah. um maybe doing that um uh with all
of the other um education and training
that you've had and I think um maybe
having that while this program is
starting to roll out just as a
refresher. Uh but I think that um so who
out there feels that this is fair to
have something like this uh additional
training?
Just raise your hands. Yeah. Okay. Um
anybody opposed to anything like this?
Do you think we need less or more hours?
Um, I think Lisa Ginsburg had her hand
up um, prior to that. Um, just going to
allow her mic. Uh, Lisa, your mic is
enabled. Uh, you can speak when ready.
>> Hi, my name is Lisa. I'm the founder of
Chunga Institute. We are in um, Oregon
and Colorado to provide certification,
training, and soc facilitation. And uh
from our experience,
I think it would be really helpful to
have clear guidelines on which
institutions would you count as
accredited programs because what we
experience people submitting the
application saying, "Oh, well, I took
this course somewhere and it was just
one person creating a course. There's no
accreditation or structure in the
course." Uh unfortunately for our
program specifically, we cannot accept
that. Uh we do accept people that are
transferring from different accredited
schools and programs that not even
accredited like um California Institute
of Integral Studies, MAPS and so on that
we can accredit and uh count towards a
program. But um I think would be really
helpful for training programs to have
clear guidelines from you guys on which
programs and certifications would be
counted towards um the transfer credits.
And um in terms of the hours, I really
appreciate the last question. I think
depending because for example Oregon's
training requirements 120 hours 25 hours
now uh in Colorado is 150 hours um
people who transferring from Oregon to
Colorado would have to complete
additional modules on ethics like
additional at least 25 hours plus we
also have to cover the regulations and
rules. So, I would think about that
because sometimes, yes, someone can be
accredited through CIS or different
programs that have outstanding
curriculum, but it might miss the most
important part of rules and regulations
that New Mexico requires. And I think
that is important for people to cover to
even protect themselves as practitioners
to be aware of the rules of regulations.
So I think it's worth to understand how
long the program is and what would be
the requirement for those hours and I
think it would require more than 6 hours
in my opinion.
>> Yeah. Well, thank you Lisa for that
because um uh that was on one of my
slides as well because I did talk to
um inner uh inner uh trek um last week
and um the 150 hours and the 120 hours.
Um that would be like start to finish
and that would be you know a program for
people that are just starting
um with um with um psilocybin
um of of course there is a big list of
accredited
um institutions and programs out there
like MAPS
um and um you know uh that would be that
would be up to the Department of Health
because there is a long list of um
accreditation
uh through these institutions and yes um
when I was talking to Interrek Lisa over
there uh we were talking about how um
some people uh yeah they have a lot of
experience but they don't have uh the
ethics they don't have uh the other
training and we've got to remember this
is a medical program and that this is
basically for people who you know have
already um have a a license. That's what
the reciprocity is all about. So yeah, I
really appreciate you um your input on
this and um uh 6 to 8 hours um I think
covering the topics and I think if we
move to the next slide I think it's in
the next slide I put that in creating a
curriculum for education from New
Mexico. Maybe we could go to the next
slide. Let's see what I have there.
Okay. Insurance liability,
training hours, licenses, billing. Okay.
Let's uh go back to the previous slide.
Um and we'll just keep it there for now.
Um so yeah I what I would like to see is
um a list
of uh the institutions the education
programs and training that do have um
all of the um requirements for our
training here in New Mexico. And so that
leads me into this, you know, what is
our uh curriculum going to look like? Um
there's a lot of different curriculums
out there. Um there are a lot of uh
hours put into this and uh I think we
could go ahead and bring up the document
at this point.
We can Jorge
And while we're doing that,
um, let's see.
>> Looks like, um, next in line with their
hand up, we've got Jen Clemente. I'm
going to
>> allow your mic. Jen, your mic is
enabled. You can talk when ready.
>> Okay. Yeah, I didn't really have a
question per se. Um, I just had raised
my hand, I think, answering one of the
questions, but let me kind of scroll
back here.
Um, no, there's nothing nothing I
haven't mentioned that others haven't.
So, I don't I don't need to ask a
question now.
>> All righty. Um, let's see. How far back
are we on the chat here? So,
uh, let's see.
Okay.
So, what we could do is here um let's
see if we can increase the
the size of the document here. Jorge, if
you can.
Okay.
And let's go ahead and uh
>> that get enough or does that get enough?
>> A little bit more. A little bit more.
>> Tell me when.
>> Okay. That's good. That's good. Okay.
>> Okay.
So, um yes, I I didn't get a uh Oh, so
hello Tom Eert. I you were mentioned by
Lisa um there at um Inner Trek um and
for the training program there and she
was kind enough to uh show me the uh
curriculum there. Uh let's go ahead and
uh scroll down a little bit.
And so, uh, yeah, let's stop right here.
Um,
so what I had in mind, let's just back
up a little bit up to the
Okay. Uh, yeah, it's kind of in between
here. Okay, let's guiding principles.
Okay. So for the first part of um you
know the curriculum here I think um uh
the framework basically here is you know
first safety and ethics
um you know prioritizing uh you physical
psychological and cultural spiritual and
moral safety of people and uh people
that we're working with. um the equity
and access reducing barriers for
historically marginal communities. Um
and let's keep scrolling up a little
bit. Okay.
Uh cultural humanity and respect. Um
honoring indigenous knowledge and
sovereignty and lineage lineage lineage
based practices and diverse spiritual
traditions. Um four is traumainformed
care recognizing the prevalence of
trauma and avoiding reharm. Five interd
disciplinary collaboration valuing
distinct clinical spiritual and cultural
community roles while fostering sharing
and understanding evidence informed
based practices integrating research and
data lived experience in clinical wisdom
and pastoral and spiritual care
frameworks. And number seven, scope of
practice and clarity and clear
boundaries based on lensure ordinate
ordination and certification and role.
And uh let's just scroll down a little
bit more.
So
and keep going to learning objectives.
Let's go there.
Okay, let's just stop right there for a
moment. So,
let's take a look at
um all of the different things that we
want to try to bring into the
curriculum. And
uh we're going to have to start writing
one up. We're going to have to start
bringing in materials and education. But
in the same time, we can look at what
others have done, you know, other
other programs that are out there right
now that can start to um we could start
to bring into New Mexico. So, um let's
see. Um, of course, we're going to be
the learning objectives
describing the historical uh, cultural
and spiritual contemporary use of
psilocybin or psilocin because I think
this is going to change a little bit
because of the um, we're we're really
looking at uh, silic silicon as the
active um, uh, medicine. Um and so that
there's language that is going to be
changing um you know in the curriculum
understanding basic neurobiological and
and psychological mechanisms of action
identifying indicator indications and
contraindications and risk factors. Um
explain ethical considerations in form
consent and power dynamics. Okay, could
scroll down a little bit more. recognize
the role of sentence setting,
preparation, ritual and integration,
understand legal and regulatory
frameworks relevant to their
jurisdiction and role. So, that one is
really important to us here in New
Mexico. We want to be able to fit this
within our um legal system here and and
keep it uh the way it needs to be. So in
this curriculum and we could go on and
on and on about what we need to have
here but let's scroll down to these core
educational domains.
Thank you.
So uh when I was saying like between six
and eight hours, I was thinking um these
core curricul uh educational domains
um can be at least one or two hours each
to cover each and every one of these
categories in the education process. So,
um I think that um those of us who are
certified or have um uh some kind of
documentation, bonafide documentation
in um our uh health care that's
recognized in the department of health.
I think having uh a review of these uh
particular education domains. So, we're
history and culture, context,
neuroscience and psychology, mental
health, spiritual care and applications.
If we could keep grow scrolling down,
ethics, consent and power dynamics. Um,
we could still keep scrolling.
Legal and regulatory overviews.
um and then we can start to maybe
incorporate what other programs have
into our program. So, um I think that
those of you who are out there educating
right now, if you do have a curriculum
that you're presently using
um that
um
creating a um
a
document or a curriculum
that you would see that could
incorporate New Mexico's culture and
other um domains here would be really
fabulous. And I think presenting that
into the the next meeting or the next
two other meetings would be really good
because then we could get on track on
things that we could be missing uh in
this document. Um change the language if
we need to. um add or um edit some of
this in this document and then uh we
could take a look at um some of these
curriculums that are out there. Um
so
my question to everyone is is that
um
what would be the best thing for us here
in New Mexico to learn from all of these
other programs?
All right. And looks like Lisa Ginsburg
has her hand up. Um let's see. Lisa, I
have enabled your mic. You can talk when
ready.
>> Uh, thank you. Um, from our experience,
uh, we see a tremendous need for, uh,
emphasis on ethics. Um, we have most of
our clients and students have a medical
license either coming from nurse
background or therapist, psychiatry. Um
however the ethics that applicable for
psychedelic therapy is significantly
different from standard ethics. Um there
is a notion of shared altered
experiences and other states that are
not covered in standard practice. Yes.
uh we talk about con um
about different types of ethical
approaches but I think that requires
minimum two hour of um going over edex
that specifically applicable for
psychedelic therapy um and I think
that's one of the few points that I
wanted to highlight uh and in general
I'm still talking about the additional
hours for someone who's transferring
their certification I
go towards increasing the requirements
because for ethics we need at least two
hours plus plus going of the rules and
regulations we're looking at minimum 10
hours if not more.
Yes, I think um ethics is one of the
biggest ones that uh need to be go to go
over and yes, Lisa, I think you are um
spot on with uh the ethics that concerns
um psychedelics because it is it is
different and there are more additional
uh things that need to be covered
ethically when it comes to psychedelics.
Like for instance, uh consent for touch.
Um if if someone is um
uh not feeling heard or um for some
reason um their identity has been uh
breached. Uh there are a lot of things
that need to be covered here. Uh I think
there are other ethical issues as well
that um uh primarily like I'm I'm a
teleaalth
clinician and there's um different
different kinds of ethics that kind of
are are there because people can walk in
the room you know there's uh there it
could easily be a breach of um
confidentiality there. So those things I
think is is very very important. Um the
the one thing that I'm very concerned
about for us here in New Mexico is that
we don't have time. And I think uh as
far as training and education goes, we
really have to we really have we're in
urgency. we have to really get a really
good robust curriculum down that will
help all of us and I think that uh the
additional training for those who are
already certified. I think that's a very
very good point. Now um uh I'm sorry I
didn't get to read everyone's um chat. I
I can't do two things at one time. So,
um, so I just wanted to say, uh, what
Kate Hawk here has. Um, uh, she says,
"These categories make sense. Number
one. Number two, some of us based on
previous training and experience qualify
for a 25-hour version of Colorado's 150
hour training that covered ethics and
Colorado's program. This was helpful
even for very experienced practitioners
and uh two whenever the initial
qualifications are I hope we can have
provisions in our system for ongoing
support after licensing. I I love this
because we will have to have ongoing
um uh education here because it's not
going to be one and done and that's it.
uh the more this uh this moves on and
we're creating this, we're and I've said
this before, we're, you know, we're
putting the plane together as we're
flying it. Um we want to be able to have
this um in place before we we start
going, but like I said before, we're
going to be pressed for time. And so
what I would like to see is um all of
those that that are certified, we
already have a program here and maybe um
uh 25 hours uh would be adequate uh for
all of us that are already certified.
And like I said before, had an ad add-on
for um uh for um additional training uh
would be great uh for all of us because
um we want to be able to satisfy what
the Department of Health has for us now.
Uh yeah, go ahead.
>> I'm sorry. I think my mic is still on
and I just want to I think that's great.
25 hours sounds really um ideal and uh a
few other things that I I looked at the
core educational domains uh which is
well structured. Um a few things that
maybe because I cannot see a full
document missing is the dosage and uh
since New Mexico does not have a
constraint on which psilocybin strain is
allowed and you guys um sounds like
we'll be allowing all type of
psilocybin. It is important to also
cover because different type of
psilocybin mushrooms have different
effect and I think that's something that
needs to be covered as well even in an
overview um including the age we see a
lot in practice with a older population
it takes time to people process the
silicab and feel the effect and they
tend to have a deeper journeys and more
uh physically uh adverse reactions. So I
think that's important also to cover
including nondirective facilitation
which also I have not seen in the core
educational domains but maybe it's
there. It's just I have a limited view
of it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. This is kind of a a short
little like screen here. Um
so
um yeah I I think that um what was it um
what you were saying about dozing and
all of that. Well, we do have a uh
dosing committee that is um and also too
they're um the propagation committee is
also talking about uh you know dosing uh
types of mushrooms um what will be um uh
allowed what you know practitioners
especially um need to be very uh
educated on the different types that are
going to be used in this and how it how
will be used. So uh we will um uh other
committees are working on that and there
is
um overlap in a lot of our committees
because of uh the the education part is
uh part of that also too it's
um kind of I I try to attend as many
meetings as I can but I know the dosage
is going to be a a big one for um
educating um us providers. So yes,
that's I I I agree with you there. Um it
it it does have to be one of those
things that we really need to um be
wellversed on.
>> All right. Um and next with their hand
up looks like uh Patricia.
Patricia, I have enabled your mic. You
can talk when ready.
Hi, thank you so much Brena. Thanks for
holding space with us. Um I think my
hand got mixed up in the the last time
we raised our hand. So my input is on
it's like five slides ago. Um but I
don't know if they're
like I think
Oh, you're breaking up.
Oh, can you hear me? Yeah, you'll have
to repeat what you said. I'm sorry.
>> That's okay. Um, back to I think your
second slide where you had the slide
regarding submitting prior training. Um,
so I was kind of curious about that
because we had some, you know, some
educators on this call. Um, and I know
we're, you know, I'm I'm here in New
Mexico. I'm a spiritual healer. I own
Invocation Healing Arts and I've been
training for the last four years to
serve here in our state. Um, but I
specifically chose not to do a
certification out of state knowing that
we didn't know our protocol here. Um, I
do have teachers who can provide like
dactic training, supervisation of that.
So, I was just curious if if your slide
if that's kind of what you meant by that
slide or um if that was
>> Yeah. Um well so um uh if you
for the sake of saying this uh in the
healing arts basically or alternative
type of not
>> you know medical or anything like that
um I see that as um also too uh if
you've been certified in in something
that should qualify be under the
umbrella of qualifications. So if we
scroll down this document, let's see,
keep going, keep going
all the way down. It's in reciprocity.
It's the last page.
Okay, hold it right there. So um uh
documentation for reciprocity review
umbrella approve. So if you have
certification of completion or
transcripts from you know other places
that uh New Mexico will approve of that
accreditation or that certification
then um uh you'll you'll be under that
umbrella of of reciprocity.
Now, um
let's see. Um let me look at the chat
here for just a moment. Um so, uh Cyena,
um McKenzie, I hope I said your name
right. Um she said in the absence of a
national certified body for the
education assessment of facilitators
rather than accepting what other states
have accepted, it may be wise to screen
and list specific programs the state of
New Mexico find best serves its unique
communities as well as uh programs that
cover contemporary needs of the state.
Um, she also says that look at what has
worked well in Colorado, Oregon and what
hasn't uh to grow and evolve from there.
And um so that that kind of is in line
with what we're talking about here like
what um what is the department of health
going to accept and what are they going
to to accept? So it's really up to them.
I mean we can go ahead and propose what
we want in uh this document um and other
meetings uh like with dosing and all of
that. That's why it's really important
for us to kind of come together and and
work with this. However, if you like for
instance, if you are a somatic healer
and you have gone through a program
uh with um working somatically with with
psychedelics, it it should be under the
umbrella um of alternative types of uh
of training. However, it has to meet um
qualifications too that the DO is going
to
uh want to have as far as licensing goes
in practice. So, um it's it's really up
to them, but I myself would love to
include everyone that has been trained
in psychedelics,
uh that uh have had ethics, for
instance, that has had um uh
classes in our historical culture here
in New Mexico. So, okay. Um who else is
up there? Can I just say one more thing?
>> Yes. Yeah, go ahead.
>> Oh, I just say I also agree with your
suggestion and that I think it was that
same slide regarding having I don't know
whether you call alocart training or
whatever that is. Um for folks who you
know like you said already have a lot of
training but maybe there's like certain
topics to brush up on or even certain
things that are specific to like our
communities here in New Mexico or even
like the four specific conditions that
were approved. Um, so yeah, I like that
idea. Thank you.
>> Yeah. And um and I like what uh I think
it was Lisa said earlier um having like
25 hours and um you know like let's say
let's say you're deficient
um in in one of the uh core curriculums
there um and you say you know uh I
really need to brush up on my ethics or
I really need to brush up on having a
practicum or you know um you know uh
maybe there's been you know more um
included in the history of New Mexico.
Maybe there was something in the a prior
curriculum that didn't make it into a
present curriculum. So um and having
this ongoing education
uh that's why in licensing you have to
get your license every two years and
have at least 12 hours of ethics. and
why couldn't psychedelic ethics be uh
part of the 12, you know, CEUs that you
need for for that? And that's just an
example. Um I think that would um uh be
very helpful for a lot of us that maybe
we missed something or you know uh just
to cover our our um you know uh our
deficiencies in our education and
training. I think that would be
wonderful. And also too, people who
moved here from other states that are
certified and have a a need to, hey,
maybe I should take this um extra these
extra um add-on classes or this
curriculum so I can, you know, really um
serve the community here in New Mexico.
All right. Anyone else?
>> All right. Next with their hand up,
we've got Tom Eert. Um Tom, I have
enabled your mic. You can talk when
ready
or unmute when ready. Sorry.
And just as a reminder, the uh mic icon
up at the top um right part of the
screen. There you go.
>> Thank you. I found it. Um yeah, thanks
for having having us. Um my name's Tom.
um executive director at Interrek and
founder of Interrek also uh was the
chair of the Oregon board back in the
day when it was just getting started and
I was also the kind of architect of the
Oregon campaign. Um so I've seen things
unfold and and what's kind of important
to me is and is
standardization of training to some
degree uh such that you know the core of
training is well understood. I mean,
there's it's in regulatory frames in in
Oregon and New Mexico and have been
looked at in different ways for some
time. Uh, and you're
uh bringing attention to, okay, how do
you customize for New Mexico? So, I
think there's kind of this this
unfolding
piece of like identifying core training,
which you know, there's a lot of a lot
of clarity there. uh just kind of a toz
what that looks like in in regs and then
thinking about what your state is kind
of um
you know kind of uniquely looking at and
you know with New Mexico you have
qualifying conditions so it seems like
there's a particular attention to um
those conditions those could be part of
uh gap education I guess you could say
so what what I'm at is there's if you
have core education, there's there's uh
lots of approved programs in Oregon,
Colorado. There's also programs that
just have commensurate um you know,
check all those boxes. You figure out
who those programs are and then you
figure out what's uh unique to to New
Mexico. So, you have whatever kind of
pieces you want to put in there. And I
just hope that that kind of unfolds in a
kind of a simplified standardized way.
Um, I think it might be
challenging to I'm not I'm trying to get
clear on how you're thinking about
evaluating
where folks are at in that process
because I'm hearing that with
credentials there's a potential for um
picking up on this education in
different places such that there's, you
know, kind of skipping through some of
the elements uh based on credentiing.
I'm not sure if I have that clear or
not. Um, but I would, you know, I would
suggest that, um, the less of that the
better. I think that, you know,
psychedelic training is pretty unique.
We have a lot of credentialed folks in
our program and we rarely feel like, you
know, oh, they already have this piece
and don't need to kind of um, do it.
Although there is some of that. Um, so
yeah, I'm thinking in those terms like
uh seems to me that the core education
piece is fairly clear and is is well
laid out in a lot of different ways.
Well, well, thank you, Tom, for your
input because um I was looking at um you
know, your
um
curriculum and a couple of other ones as
well. And um I like to lean into like
simple is the best way to do things
because I think once you start putting
more things in there, the more
complicated it gets. Um, I just wanted
to read some things in the chat real
quick before we um take um uh some more
people that have their hands raised. Um,
let's see. Um, let's see. Jen Clemente
says, "Ongoing support for me would look
like opportunities to practice sitting,
roleplaying, simulation, and group
support to discuss various scenarios
that come up." That's that's a great
one. Um yes, I think practicum is is a
really um good good way to learn. Um and
let's see, Michelle uh says uh perhaps
just like teaching license practitioners
are required to to complete x and number
of cus to stay current and revalent.
That's that's great. That I like that as
well. Um uh Gregory says um we're
starting with repres reciprocity. That's
the wrong place. starting point before
we talk about reciprocity transfer or
amending trend uh training we need to
define what New Mexico's program
actually requires that baseline doesn't
exist yet you can't evaluate what
transfers until you know what it's
transferring into New Mexico is doing
something different Oregon and Colorado
are not our model the structure we build
here needs to reflect that I think we
need role specific requirements before
anything else. Each role has a distinct
scope and a distinct risk profile.
Absolutely. Um you know uh referring uh
clinician screening competency cont uh
indications knowledge informed consent
high stakes on um uh patient rate
selection. Yes. administration click um
clinicians the core practitioner role
heaviest training requirements sessions
management safety response
pharmarmacology
integration therapists pre and post
preparation integration frameworks
existing lensure probably carries the
most transfer value here and support
personnel do we have sitters monitors if
yes what's the minimum compa um
competency floor this needs a decision
not an assumption
on uh
uh credentiing question. I don't think
formal education equates uh capacity.
I'm also not suggesting we disregard
educational institutions. The real
question is whether the credential maps
to the competency we're actually
requiring. Define the competency domains
first. Then ask what pathways
demonstrate them. formal education
supervision hours demonstrated practice
lived experience um don't use a degree
as proxy for readiness and once new New
Mexico requirements are defined
reciprocity becomes attractable question
does the applicant's prior training meet
our standards what carries over what
needs a bridge until we answer those
reciprocity decisions are circular and
yes um this document does include a lot
of um what you um stated here. Um the
reason why I'm starting with reciprocity
here is because um we don't have a lot
of time and we have to start with people
who are already trained and uh what will
that look like? Um and that's why I'm
starting here because our first meeting
was um uh going over a lot of um what
you had mentioned and so um this is a
medical uh program. So starting off with
um medical providers right now is
probably going to be the first thing and
uh the other um certifications will be
um coming in as well and also too you
know what qualifies people. Uh so uh
that's up to the department of health to
see uh which programs are going to be
implemented into uh the department of
health and what they see is going to be
um the right
avenue to go down in
um let's see before I read any more chat
um let's see who who has their hand
raised Gregory. Yeah. And that's
actually a good time because Greg's the
next hand up. And I think your mic is
still enabled, Greg. So you can unmute
when ready.
>> Hey, cool. Yeah, just to
shape all that wall of text I dumped on
you.
>> Um, I'm thinking about this from a
product development perspective. I'm
>> not an educator and I'm not like, you
know, a doctor, but I am an expert in
putting planes together while they are
in the air. I've done this in several
types of ways throughout my life. So, if
we're looking at building a program, we
need to get to the requirements before
we start building. And so, as soon as
you have all of those requirements in
place, then the reciprocity just falls
in. So, we require that you have this
qualification and I can pull this
qualification out of my pocket and show
you, hey, I have this widget and now we
can move forward. But wait, I'm missing
one thing. How do we fulfill the need of
educating and qualifying that person to
fit the requirements and get this moving
super fast? Because we have people in
the room right here who can
do all of the things that we need today.
Um it's just a matter of defining those
requirements before we start like
circular
um going through the circular logic of
well how do we how do we do reciprocity
before we know what we're um
putting that into I guess.
>> Okay. Um yeah. Um so
>> one other thing sorry.
>> Yeah go ahead. um when it comes to the
the dosage conversation, I would be more
than happy to um
write that section for you.
>> Okay. Um uh and I think you've been
going to the uh dosing meetings and uh
haven't you?
>> Yeah. And beyond that, like I've I've
already got like a I've been working on
understanding analytics and dosage for
years and I have the workings of uh
publications in place and a deep
understanding of how um unique
chemotypes affect experience and how to
analyze those and how to communicate
that in a very simple way. But yeah,
that's down the road.
>> Okay. Uh thank you. Thank you for that
uh uh Greg. Um, okay. So, let's scroll
up to the top. Let's start from the
beginning there cuz Yeah. Uh, just so
that that doesn't confuse people
anymore. So, at least um get the first
the purpose of this document right there
and we could scroll up and and see that.
Um, so yes, I think um uh bringing all
of that in. Yeah, we're um
I think the dosing and the education
part is going to be a a big one because
um um maybe some clinicians uh won't
feel comfortable with that and you know
uh then you know what what if we didn't
do them a really good service of
training them and feeling comfortable
with dosing. So that that has a lot to
do with um the training process and how
much do you dose somebody and all of the
contraindications that may be um you
know falling through the cracks that uh
people really need to learn and be
trained with. Yeah, absolutely. Uh let's
see. I will um read another chat here.
It says um from Katherine uh one thing
that we will be doing different from the
other states is practicum. This will
provide a level of training that doesn't
exist in Colorado and otherwise. I
believe in other states they are too
heavy on lecture and we can require less
but also require practicum which gives
much more overall training than just
lectures. Uh let's see. I'll just read a
couple more and then we'll um go to um I
guess James here. Um I think he's next.
Um also uh the core educational domains
would cover integration. Um I think we I
think I might have that in there in this
document. Um I'm glad there was mention
of dosage related to age. I don't recall
factors of working with older patients
being emphasized in any of my previous
trainings except for end of life care.
Working with older population is
significant
specialty something that everyone should
have awareness of. And yes, I'm a senior
by the way. Uh that I that never
occurred to me either. I think that
that's a very important part and um I
think that should be looked at as well.
um and and and brought into the
curriculum.
Excuse me. Okay. Um I'll just um
hold it right here. Okay. I think James
Brown is next. Is James next?
>> Whoops. Um yes. Okay. I have enabled
your mic. things
>> Brendan everyone you know my thought on
this too going back to what was said
earlier standardization
um as we're the third state
in a unique position
you know right now it's it's very key
that we standardize our training with
some of the other standardizations
already going on with the curriculum
that's currently available
so if we say that Oregon's 120 and
they're growing every year. They keep
passing more and more hours. And we say
Colorado is 150. In order to do that
reciprocity, we have to minimally say
that we're going to have around 120 150
or more. And so just a thought there,
right? Just kind of standardize. I
really like that idea because there is
no other governing board out there, but
there will be. And when that governing
board comes, how are they going to look
at our program? Or are we going to be
the people that help set those trends
and help set that board, which I'm
hoping happens for New Mexico? And so,
>> absolutely. Yeah, James, I think you're
Yeah. Yeah. I think you're uh you know
you're really on on that and I think um
that um we we there has to be a
standardization of accreditation for
this because um like I'm Maps trained
and I think that was um gez I I counted
as months it was like six seven months
that the the training was there and so
um why we we shouldn't really I I I
really I'm I'm hearing what you're
saying this program should be really
robust, but it shouldn't be watered down
either. And that this should incorporate
a lot of the standards that we're we're
seeing that other states are doing,
other institutions are um incorporating
and that uh we should also have that as
well. Uh if we um because a lot of these
programs are
specially trained, you know, we have
these trainings to have this so we can
>> move it along that we that be we need to
do this like now. However, um I think uh
we only have till December. So uh to get
this rolled out uh in a manner that um
we are doing it safely and ethically and
incorporating um you know our culture
and also um you know the dosing part of
it is I I think one of the main things
that makes a lot of us nervous because
uh of course we want to have um um
something there a a a standard to go by
that we're um giving you know the
medicine in a proper and correct way.
Okay, who else do we have here?
>> Looks like ne next we have uh Chris
Caldwell and I have enabled your mic.
>> Yeah. Hi everyone. Nice to be here. Um,
I want to sort of echo what I heard Greg
say because um, New Mexico is not like
Colorado or Oregon. You are a medical
model and Bren just said it yourself a
little bit ago. You're going to have um,
medical clinicians, mental health
clinicians needing to be trained. Um,
when I build a course for uh,
physicians, it's very different than
building a course um, that's more uh,
that's that's that's for more
disciplines. Um and and so um I I I
strongly recommend you know you you step
back and like what Greg said you know
what are the requirements here and who
will you be training um uh has to be
looked at first um I mean for example
the and when you have a non-medical
model preparation and integration does
not in uh encompass anything taking into
account let's say a licensed social
worker um here you should be you know
it's not totally non-directive. You're
talking about people who can practice
psychotherapy and and they should be
practicing psychotherapy. If a clinical
chaplain becomes part of that team, then
you know their training will include um
their license work um preparation and
integration. So I I think you're talking
about a very very different type of
training. Quite frankly, I like the
core. Um, any of the non-medical models
can clearly deliver on the the core and
much of the skills
I saw was missing in part two skills was
like self-care and safety by the way.
Um, and I think there should be a module
on on inter disciplinary collaboration
as well. Um, but I'd be looking at a
Pratty group or I'd be looking at
Polaris or anybody who's been training
physicians and clinicians.
>> Well, well, thank you for that. I think
yeah, we we do have to um kind of stay
focused on the medical model here. um
you know later on um anyone who who is
practicing in healing arts uh per se is
um you know they also t too need to be
um educated. I think um I think it might
have been
um I guess Lita Fati in her last
meeting. I think it was her that said
that um have um
have the training
that everybody can have. But um as you
were saying it's like the medical model
is different for people who um don't
have that the the the medical training.
So um yeah you you could do that however
and it could be cost effective. Uh
however um uh I see it as a little
different and that there there has to be
maybe now I could be wrong um have two
different types of education with that.
So, like you were saying, if a um if a
uh uh like let's say a a priest wanted
to to to to do this, um yes, he's you
know, he has credentials and licensed or
whatever and is it it it takes this this
class. Um I I don't know. I don't I I
really now that I'm kind of talking in
through my head about it um I really
don't know
personally
um if the medical model
or the medical training would encompass
that. So um yeah, if I can have other
people talk about that. Well, I I I
would like to finish my thought because
I I maybe I should not have said
anything about a clinical chaplain
because you went down a totally
different path than what I was talking
about. Um you know, and basically you
keep talking about there's no time,
there's no time. Well, I think you know,
you need to build the right program to
deliver the best service. And if you
need to push back the start of this
program, then push back the start of
this program or limit its roll out. you
you know that was arbitrary. You started
you started first with December 31st,
and then whomever decided they were
going to push it back or push it up to
uh to 2026. You know, that was arbitrary
and and so you need you need a a good
strong program. Again, you're a medical
model. You're not a non-medical model.
>> All right, I'm done. Thank you.
>> Yeah, thank you. Thank you. All right.
Um let's see. Uh
okay. Um
all right. So um and um Ellen said there
is no specific number of didactic hours
needed. We need to look at competency
not number of hours.
Um let's see an um it's in students best
interest to have standardization.
It may also allow them to also work with
FDA approved psychedelics if we align
with other states.
Um Eileen said I don't know what we will
ever do that because we were all seeing
the issues with the requirements in
other states and we are learning from
those. So we are still in the wild west
of figuring this out. It's true. Um uh
uh Jeremy Rudy says uh once we know the
role specific competencies required for
New Mexico
uh Saba practis can offer an alternative
option for practicums and competencies
assessments that wasn't available when
Oregon and Colorado programs were were
stood up. All I think it's wise to have
a reciprocity option for uh past
training. We can directly verify
proficiency through our all powered uh
simulation environment.
Um let's see. Uh
>> and I think that said AI powered, but
>> that's okay. Um
let's see. Eene says um
uh but we don't know what that might
look like right now. It's one of those
things that was challenged in discussing
with LICO application. Further
applications may not even tie the
substance to uh PAT and James said um
James Brown said we need to ensure that
there is continuation education for
facilitators for each lency renewal
process. Yes. And we need to ensure that
the program allows access to New
Mexicans across the whole state for
those who want to be trained. Okay. Um,
uh, let's see who's, um, who has their
hand next.
>> Um, looks like Ellen Shimls.
Um, oh, I do see Dominic has his hand
raised. Um, Dominic is is yours a quick
tidbit or
attention.
>> I will wait in turn.
>> Okay, cool.
>> So, go ahead.
>> All right. So, Ellen, I have enabled
your mic.
>> Thanks. Um, my name's Ellen Shims. I'm a
nurse practitioner in Albuquerque. And I
just wanted to kind of caveat on what I
just said. I agree that we should
definitely have reciprocity, but I think
the best way to show that is to really
look at a competency based model. um
things like BLS like when you look at
you know all the all of us medical
providers get regular BLS and BLS has
already got an amazing model that we
could be looking at using things like
simulation and and I know what was
mentioned some of the AI driven and
other there's other platforms that are
available that really we could take our
learners into situations that are
challenging that they don't have the
opportunity typically that we don't want
them to have the opportunity to have in
the learning environment with either one
another as patients or real or real
patients in that capacity. I think that
we have a chance to do something
different here to make it a more
affordable because I know you know I've
been through IPI. I've been through
these medical trainings and there are
thousands and thousands of dollars. I
don't know how we're going to afford
that for training people here as well.
So that does concern me is looking at
other routes that we could use
technology that we could use more
competency based where people are
showing that they have the skill set if
they've already you know that that
automatically puts that reciprocity
there because they're showing they're
competent in the things that they've
already learned. Um and so I just think
that we should I get standardization but
I think that it is not a
one-sizefits-all. To say that everyone
needs 150 hours is silly. That's not how
we educate these days. and we really
need to look at competencies. Thanks.
>> Thank you for that. Um, yes. Um, well, I
think when we're when we're saying 150
hours or 120 hours, I think what we're
saying there is for pe for people who
are just starting and want to get uh
want to get that education
um for um I think the reciprocity part
of it. Um, I think having, you know,
some hours that we have in our
education,
uh, for New Mexico would, um, be an
additional to what we've already been
trained in. So, I think adding that that
other part of it, uh, once we get the
training down, um, I think we'll be able
to start to, um, get this rolled out,
but I think, um, reinventing the wheel
is not what we should be doing.
Absolutely. Everybody's saying we have
so many other things that we could pull
into the training of uh document here
that I think that we'll be able to um uh
probably get this together pretty soon,
but we need to look at what um the
curriculum is going to be and um who's
going to be do doing the teaching and
who's who is going to be providing that.
So, um, yeah.
>> All right, Dominic. Um, you should be
good.
>> Yes. Thank you, Johnny. And thank you,
Brenda and Ellen, thank you very much
for some of the comments you just made.
It actually dovtales very well in what I
wanted to state at this point is I think
everybody is starting to kind of jump
ahead a little bit here is what we need
to be looking at is we need to be
looking at competencies at skills. We
need to look at what lensures
individuals already have. the statute is
actually very clear that uh the
practitioners or the providers need to
be current licensed individuals in
healthcare in New Mexico. And so one of
the things that we're doing is we're
actually cobbling together a list of all
of those potential lensures that already
exist here in New Mexico. Once we have
that, we're going to be looking at
different aspects of what types of
training they already have, what types
of training they may need in order to do
work within uh psychedelic therapeutic
environments, how that actually might
work. We are also looking at curricula
that are available through some of these
other programs that have been approved
by both Colorado and Oregon. And as we
look at that, we need to be evaluating
what parts and pieces are going to be
appropriate for New Mexico, what parts
and pieces may be a little bit too much
and not necessarily needed. Um, but
we're not trying to sit there at this
initial stage and try to limit by hours.
When educational programs are developed,
if people turn around and say something
like there's 150 hours that we need to
complete for this program, what happens
is instead of evaluating the actual
needs of the education aspect of it,
people try to then fit it in within that
particular time frame. So what I would
really suggest for right now is let's
not talk about how many hours are needed
or not hour needed. How many hours does
Oregon Oregon do? How many hours does
Colorado do? We need to look and
evaluate. And to my knowledge, because
I've been looking and if somebody,
especially some of those who are
involved and have been involved in some
of those programs uh in the other
states, if there is an evaluation of the
efficacy of the training program, I
would love to see it and I would love to
be able to start looking at that. Many
people that are on this call may not
realize or know um because since I work
at DOH and in public health, but my my
degrees and my education is actually in
educational psychology. So developing
this. So I've been listening to hear
what people want, what's going to work
for people, what people's needs are so
that we can help to shape this in a way
that's going to be as beneficial as
possible. So what we would like though
is we want to ensure as we build this we
build it in a way that's going to
acknowledge reciprocity issues and and
for that we do as has been said by a few
people we need to know what competencies
we want to have with the providers here
in New Mexico. What aspects do we need
to do that are not included in any other
programs that include specific items to
New Mexico including cultural
traditional uh healing and other areas
and how do we create that? So I wouldn't
say we need to create a New Mexico
module that'll be six to eight hours or
or that side. While that can be a good
start, we need to create a New Mexico
module and we've stated before
Department of Health will create that
module with regard to folks that as we
determine and as Brenda has said, we
have not yet determined what those
reciprocity qualifications will be, but
we will create that and make that
available to anybody who needs that. So
that'll be whether it's individuals,
training programs or whomever so that
they can actually make we can make sure
that they understand the environment
they're coming into the populations in
New Mexico so that we can ensure that
patients in New Mexico are getting uh
not just patient centered care but New
Mexico centered care and I think that's
going to be a very important aspect. So,
as we look at all of this and as we
discuss this, let's think about it from
a standpoint of what is it that patients
need? there may be programs that are out
there that are going to align with that
or that they need a little bit of
tweaking, a little bit of, you know,
extra support or maybe even not as much
because the other aspect that is come to
us in I can't even begin to say how much
public comment and emails and messages
is affordability.
So many people, especially people in New
Mexico, are not going to be able to
afford a program that costs8 to $15,000
in order to get training, especially if
it's somebody who already has a
therapist license, uh, you know, so
clinical social worker, etc. And so, we
need to make sure that we do this in a
way that's going to acknowledge that and
is as affordable as possible. doesn't
mean it's going to be free, but we want
to try to make it so it's as affordable
and accessible as possible. Uh I've
noticed some notes and and we've gotten
before as far as having things with
virtual training. We do want to ensure
that there's virtual training because we
also have a lot of individuals who may
be working out of frontier and rural
areas and they're going to be able to
help those patients in those areas. If
we mandate that it must be inperson for
an entire training program, that would
be problematic. So, we need to make sure
there's that flexibility
um so that patient or that uh providers
can actually do these programs, do them
at their speed that's going to be
appropriate because how many of and and
for people who are on right now, how
many of you currently have a different
job? And so to be able to learn and do
that facilitation, we need to think
about things not just in-person but also
asynchronous virtual, synchronous
virtual and uh and James I think is the
one who put it in about in-person
practicums that inperson to develop
those interpersonal skills which are
going to be so key will be very
important for this. But how much time is
that really going to take? We need to
look at how do we evaluate that and no
matter what we do from the very
beginning we're one of the aspects we
have to have is an evaluation component
so that in a year two years we can
adjust the training and the training
requirements to meet what we find is
actually effective and so far I haven't
seen that with the other programs so
again if somebody else has access to
something like that and can share that
we would be happy to look at it. So,
that's really just all I had to say.
I've been listening and trying to stay
back so that people can talk, but I want
to let everybody know we are hearing
you. We are trying to, you know, trying
to figure out how to do this and we are
taking the time. We, yes, we do not have
a lot of time for December, but that's a
part of where the reciprocity comes in.
And will we always get everything right?
Probably not. But I can tell you right
now and I already know in knowing
several of the people that are here
already, we have some fantastic
facilitators already present in the
state. And that's how this program is
going to start in December because we
already have a fair amount of these
skills and these abilities resident here
right now. Anyway, I'm going to shut up
right now. I'm going to and let
everybody continue to talk. So thank you
everybody and the conversation is great
to have. Um so please continue.
>> Thank you Dominic for that because um I
think that was kind of in everybody's
mind. It's like okay how is you know how
is this going to how are people going to
afford this? And that was in my last
slide actually. I had like cost training
and lenture and all of that. I kind of
well maybe Dominic's gonna come in here
and and and say something because I
wanted to kind of leave this open
because I think talking about all of
these different things that are coming
into um the education and training um I
think the competency is really something
that maybe we can work on uh in our next
meeting and and see what that's going to
look like as far as uh what the
training's going to
So, uh, you know, thanks for jumping in
like you did.
>> All right. Um, let's see. I think next
with their hand up, we've got, uh, Lisa
Ginsburg again. Uh, Lisa, I have enabled
your mic.
>> Thank you. And I just wanted to build on
Dominic just said um having virtual uh a
mixture of virtual and self-paced
content for deductic education is I
think totally feasible and that's how we
usually
have our training uh designed in
Colorado and Oregon and we see a lot of
success with that. Um I think also the
highlight for the inperson and humanto
human skill is really crucial for the
practicum and what we observe that
sometimes when people actually in a real
physical space you deal not only with
personalities but also with energies of
the people and that significantly
changes the environment and it's
something that I think really important
to keep in mind and have that human
component. as well that unfortunately at
the moment artificial intelligence
cannot replace and I think that's
something that should be preserved and
celebrated that we have different
personalities and energies and the
inerson practicum is really important
for practitioners regardless if they
have years of psychiatry psychology
experience is very different for
psychedelics.
Thank you.
>> Absolutely. Thank you Lisa. That that's
so true. I mean, when you're working
with a client, uh, you have to be
present and you have to know how to work
with that client and doing that in
person is is vital. Uh, this is a a a
you know, we we can't be replaced by
machines to do that. We this is a very
human uh interactive. You have to you
have to be very empathetic. You have to
uh tune into the client. you have to um
uh see what the client's needs are even
if they um h are having a difficult time
going through the journey. So there is
that practicum piece that's so very
important and um especially if we do
roll out the program where let's say we
do have 120 hours of um from start to
finish for those who do not have any
experience with psychedelics. It in u a
medical uh clinical way. They're
learning this um you know practice
practicum is one of the key things um
that um experiential type of uh
education uh you can't get that from
reading a book. You you have to be
present with with the the patients.
Absolutely.
So, anybody else have any comments?
Um I don't see any hands raised right
now but uh James Brown just posted in
the comments idea on NM specific modules
for the core training and for the
reciprocity training ICD10 codes and
billing of insurance specific to the
program safety to include personal bias
New Mexico treatment conditions and New
Mexico specific practicum settings.
Yeah, I think the ICD codes are um very
very important and I don't um you know
I've been attending a lot of these
meetings and we don't know right now
what that looks like. Um and especially
with Medicaid and Medicare uh because we
are one of the poorest states in the
nation uh we uh for practitioners uh
like myself the majority of my clients
are Medicaid and Medicare. So, uh, if
the insurance companies
miraculously say, "Okay,
um, psychedelic therapy will have its
own code." Great. But I think for right
now, I think a lot of people are just
who are underground are just if they are
doing billing hours, they're just
billing it as a regular um, therapy
session. But it needs to have its own
specific code in order for insurance
companies to have this. So um yeah, the
other thing too is safety um uh a
personal bias. Yes, absolutely. And this
is done in training. Um if uh a
clinician is um has a personal bias
um uh the thing to do is to refer them
to another clinician that can um you
know uh as far as uh uh treatments and
conditions go. Um yeah that needs to be
uh we need to have a standard there. Uh
what um what is the treatment going to
be? We have to have a set
type of way of doing this and doing it
in a very respectful and um client
centered um way of doing this. Uh yes, a
lot of us clinicians and nurses and and
and us in the medical field are trained
in that. But yeah, psychedelics is is is
different because it it is more
it is more um
um intimate than just regular talk
therapy for instance. Uh there's uh
elements to psychedelic therapy that are
almost hard to describe the relationship
between the provider and the patient.
uh it you are there on their journey and
you are taking care of them in a very
different way than say just giving them
a pill and talking about their issues.
Uh this is going to be uh paramount to
to practicum. Um, and the other thing,
yeah, uh, that leads me into the
practicum settings. Um, where will this
be done? And that that's always been one
of my biggest questions. Where will it
be done? Will it be done in a hospital
setting? Uh, will it be done um in a
clinic? Um, I've heard uh people saying
that it's it's difficult to do it in
people's homes. However, if there's
death and dying, they can't make it to,
you know, a center for instance. So,
what is that going to look like? What is
the environment going to look like? What
are people going to feel comfortable
with? Uh, remember this is the medical
model and um to have um ceremony
uh with it. Why not uh why not have
someone come in and provide ceremony for
um someone who for instance is dying? So
there's a lot that we really need to
think about as far as these topics go.
Um I think creating a real robust way of
training people in different settings in
different types of um uh
circumstances. Uh for instance, if
someone is
um dealing with chronic pain, um it's
going to be different from dealing with
someone who is um having issues with
anxiety and depression.
So, James, um anybody else uh have any
comments at this point?
Well, if you um so um has I I just want
a show of hands of of people who who
have read this document.
Okay. Um, I can I can go ahead and read
through this document, which probably
was something I should have done in the
beginning. Um, this document, I think,
um, yeah, we need to post this. So, uh,
uh, we only have, um, I guess about 20
minutes or so. I could go ahead and read
through this document if you like, and I
should have done that. Pardon me. I
really apologize for that. Um, uh, let
me read through this document and, um,
and then, uh, we can post it, uh, I
think on the site.
Yes, we will post it again uh on um uh
what with the minutes and also the
video.
>> Okay. Uh do you think we have time to
read it or should we just post it?
Dominic
>> Brenda, that's what I was going to
suggest is to let people do that. It is
actually on the site already and I'm
going to um put it uh here in the chat.
Um so just so that everybody is aware,
we do put the documents for various
meetings. Um there is uh it's on the web
page and I'm going to put that in as
well. Um and so that is under uh if you
don't see that under the direct link
there it is uh under the 2026 tab for
the medical psilocybin committee meeting
records and it was on January 23rd when
we had the last meeting and there's you
can see the recording the presentation
this document um uh and then there was a
training requirements and qualitative
analysis from HAF that they had
submitted as part of the public record
and all of that is there on on that page
with that direct link. So, what I would
suggest since there's just about 20
minutes to the end of the meeting is for
people to read through it to go to it,
read through it for the next meeting.
Um, just because otherwise I I don't
think you'd have enough time, Brenda, to
even read through. So
>> well, you know, the next time I think um
uh I will uh go ahead and read through
it again. Uh because if anybody um needs
to make any changes there, uh do do you
think that's appropriate for next time?
Yeah, I think going through section by
section like we we had done would be a
good way to do it so people could
highlight and understand and answer
specific to those sections rather than
trying to go through all of it all at
once. And so I would say go through
section by section.
>> Okay. Great. Thank you. I I it it was
one of those things where um I uh for
the second meeting I just wanted to do
see uh do something a little different.
Um, and uh, oh, I I'm glad because I got
different results this time and which
was really I think people really needed
to talk about all of this and uh, and
and I'm grateful for the people that
were from Oregon and Colorado, people
that um, have already done a lot of
training. Uh, I I'm really grateful for
all of your input here today. It it's
been amazing and it's eyeopening to and
very refreshing to have all of these
comments come in about formulating what
we need to do for our education here in
New Mexico. So, I want to thank every
one of you for being here today and your
comments.
>> And Brenda, what I would also like to
say is just um because I've gotten a
couple of emails from individuals that
they send them just to me. And what I
would actually suggest is if you have
public comment or potential resources,
not to send them directly to just me.
Quite frankly, I I get overwhelmed with
email sometimes, as I'm sure some others
do. But we do have multiple people who
look at our medical psilocybin email.
And so I'm going to put up uh the
information uh what what needs to be
done as far as for uh oh and Jorge
actually did it while I was talking for
how to send in public comment. But also
if you have resources just remember
please keep it limited you know because
otherwise what ends up happening and it
has happened is we quite literally get
thousands of pages and we're not able to
read through that much. We need it
specified, reduced down to what are you
looking at, what do you want us to look
at, um, a little bit of a summary, and
really making sure that it's brief and
short. And so the email, if you've sent
something, please resend it to that main
email because again, we do have
different staff who are helping with
different aspects and different pieces.
And so they'll be able to take that,
look at it. If it's something for public
comment, we'll put it in the public
comment. if it's just for our
information, we'll be able to, you know,
to pull that on out and, uh, look at
that as separately. So, uh, just but
thank you everybody and thank you for
posting that, Jorge.
>> Thank you, Dominic, for that too. And I
wanted to let a lot of people know
because a lot of people have my email as
well that if you do have a comment, you
this is this is public. So, you need to
bring it publicly because I um I'm not
going to go in there and start changing
the document. This is this is a public
document. So, if if you have any ideas
or you need to change anything, please
come to the meetings and um change it in
will change it in these meetings. But um
I I'm not comfortable with uh changing
anything in this document unless it's
public.
Okay. Anybody have any other comments or
would like to um
um say anything at this moment?
Okay. Uh Dominic, do you think it's
proper to end the meeting at this point?
>> I I think so. The only thing I would say
is uh for the next meeting.
>> Ah, for the next meeting. Okay. So the
next meeting will be April 10th uh from
1 to 3 for the education and training uh
for the medical civil assignment
program. Please bring your comments and
uh any notes that you have or any
information you want to bring in. Uh
this was a wonderful meeting. I think I
want to thank all every one of you. This
is uh wonderful and I know how hard it
is on a Friday to take time from your
regular jobs to come and sit at these
meetings and it's it it is it is hard to
pull away but it's so very important and
um I love all of your enthusiasm with
this especially people I want to say
thank you to everyone outside of New
Mexico coming here and giving your uh
wealth of information to us because uh
we are really starting to make this
happen here. So, thank you everyone.
Thank you. And thank you, Jorge. Thank
you so much for doing everything.
You're very wonderful. Thank you. And
thank you, Dominic.
>> Thank you to everybody. Thank you,
Brenda, so much for chairing the
meeting. And uh we look forward to the
next one.